as we continue now with our study of the
history of ideas
I've mentioned before that when I used
to teach philosophy in the University
and I found that many students
particularly beginning students had
great difficulty making the adjustment
from other disciplines and other courses
to this abstract Arena of philosophy and
so I would tell them as they were
looking at the various philosophers I
said try to discern as you're studying
these philosophers what problem they
were trying to solve because if you
understand the problem that the
philosophers are grappling with it goes
a long way to help you understand
the way in which they think and the
reasons that they go on the paths that
they go now here we are having finished
our little overview of 17th century
rationalism and we've introduced John
Locke as really the key figure for the
18th century response to rationalism
which is called empiricism and I have
told you that throughout the history of
philosophy the two major concerns and
issues by no means the only issues that
philosophers are concerned with but the
two major ones have been metaphysics
and epistemology
and I've said that in the 17th and 18th
century in this debate between the
rationalists and the empiricists the
focal point of the discussion tends to
be on epistemology
but that can be a little bit misleading
because even though we distinguish
between epistemology which you recall is
the science of knowing
how we learn how we know what we know
and metaphysics is the Quest for
Ultimate Reality that which is real but
above and beyond those things that we
perceive with the senses or the outward
realm of physics and so we make this
distinction between metaphysics and
epistemology but as I've said many times
we can distinguish them but we cannot
really separate them
because it was not simply that the
rationalists and the empiricists of the
17th and 18th century
were merely occupied with the question
of how we know things
But ultimately
they were concerned about the reality
that we're trying to know
so they never abandoned that quest for
knowing the real world now again I want
to go back and do some uh review work
you remember when we looked at Plato
I said that Plato was very much
concerned with the task of Science and
philosophy to save the phenomena
and what that meant for Plato was we
encounter all these things that appear
to us in our daily ordinary experience
those things that appear to us are the
phenomena
of Life the phenomena of this world
and what the philosopher and scientist
was trying to accomplish in Antiquity
was to come up with a theory or a system
of thought or a worldview
that would make sense
of all this widely diverse phenomena
and so
the different theories in philosophy
have been attempts to construct an
understanding of reality that would give
us some kind of possibility for science
because that's what science is science
is about knowledge an attempt to
understand the world around us the world
outside of us
and so we have two questions here what
is really out there
and how do we get to it and I've also
said in the past that what we're
wrestling with is What's called the
subject
object
problem let's again go over that quickly
I am a thinking subject I am an
individual person
and I find myself here in a world that
exists outside of me
and I as a subject am trying to come to
an awareness or an understanding of the
objective world that exists apart from
me
but remember back when we talked about
Augustine and the bent ore in the water
the world is not always as we perceive
it to be
so there's the question that links
epistemology and metaphysics
how can I overcome the limitations of my
view of the world and get to real truth
again historically
the science of epistemology is not just
simply how do we learn and how do we
gain knowledge but is also concerned
with how can we achieve certainty
how can we know what we know
for sure
and get out of Plato's Cave of Shadows
and of opinion and of idle speculation
and pure guesswork
solve the problem of the subject
relating to the object the objective
world
and we've seen that the two basic
methods that scientists and philosophers
have followed historically are deduction
and induction
deduction and induction now you hear
about deduction when you hear the
stories see them on TV or read the books
of Sherlock Holmes
and Sherlock Holmes comes to the scene
of the crime and he takes his magnifying
glass out and he and he thinks about
what he's observed
and he deduces uh the the actual crime
scene what actually happened and even
who done it
and
his assistant Dr Watson will say you
know if Sherlock College you figure that
out and he will say Elementary my dear
Watson and then you'll get another
experience of this Keen acute way of
deducing things that he was fond of
doing
and we've mentioned that induction
is where we move to knowledge by
observing or encountering little data
bits out there in the world and we move
from the particular
to the general or Universal
now what does that mean well here's how
it works
I look at a squirrel
never seen a squirrel before
somebody says oh there's a squirrel now
look at the squirrel and I see that this
squirrel has a bushy tail
so I associate bushy tails with
squirrels and I look at the second
squirrel and it has a bushy scale and a
third one a fourth one a fifth one a
sixth one I look at a hundred squirrels
and every squirrel that I look at has a
bushy tail
now I don't have time to explore every
nook and cranny of the universe and to
examine the makeup of every conceivable
squirrel that lives in the universe
but after a certain number of
repetitions of observations of
particular squirrels what do we do we
generalize
and we come to the conclusion
that all squirrels have bushy tails
simple isn't this how we do science
but you notice when we see the opinion
polls that are taken where a group of
individuals are questioned about certain
things how they're going to vote in the
next election or what what is their view
of the latest Scandal coming out of the
White House or whatever it may be
and then whenever we're done with the
polls they'll tell us
that there is a
a an error margin there of plus or minus
say three percent now why do the
pollsters tell us that
maybe it's because they don't want to
have the same thing happen that happened
in the 1948 election between Harry
Truman and Thomas Dewey where the
Chicago paper when they went to when
everybody went to bed that night it
seemed like it would be a victory for uh
Dewey and so when the paper went the
press that you had big bold headlines
that says Dewey wins but in fact
that we didn't win during the night the
momentum shifted and the election went
to Harry Truman and so there was a case
where they had sampled enough returns to
come to a conclusion
but when they got more information in
the hopper they had to change their
conclusion
now I illustrate that because these are
things that we see every day in our
lives
and yet they indicate the built-in
problem with induction
the built-in limit to this method of
knowing
and the limit is this nobody has ever
examined
every squirrel that can be found
and what if suddenly we come upon not
one squirrel but 15 squirrels that don't
have bushy tails
now we have to change our whole theory
about squirrels don't we because here we
have examples of squirrels that don't
fit our Universal or general description
of squirreliness
in fact maybe if you've been listening
carefully in the last five or so minutes
you have a much more astute
understanding of squirreliness but
you're associating it not so much with
bushy-tailed animals but with
bushy-haired philosophers but in any
case this is the problem that we have
built in
to science
built in to the inductive method
and it's even built in to language as we
will see
now so when we look at the difference
between deduction and induction
we'll go back and review this bidding
with deduction we have the famous
syllogism
that you've all heard of all men are
mortal
Socrates is a man
therefore
Socrates
is mortal
now here's the question
if this premise which we'll call premise
a
is true
and if premise B is true
if those two propositions are true
how certain could we be about the
conclusion
in terms of zero to a hundred percent
would we have to put a margin of error
of three percent
in terms of this conclusion
no we could eliminate the percentage of
possible error entirely but again that's
only if
all men are mortal and if Socrates is a
man then we can know with resistless
logic with what we call formal certainty
absolutely that Socrates is mortal
again this is based upon the formal
rules of logic and the laws of immediate
inferences if all men are mortal if
everybody in this particular class that
is men
share a common attribute or predicate
which is mortality
and then we find a particular example of
an individual human
if all individual humans that make up
this class of men
have the same attribute of mortality
then we would know with absolute
certainty that this particular
individual that we've just encountered
is mortal
so the formal process of reasoning
from propositions in terms of logical
deductions
yield
certainty
but if I just come up to you and I say
Roger amundsen is Mortal this particular
human being is mortal
how would I know that
that that's true
if he's still alive
or to put the question another way do we
really know that all men are mortal
or do we assume that all men are mortal
how do we know that all men are mortal
what have we done
we have through the process of induction
examined
Millions upon millions and millions of
individual human beings and find that
they all died
and so in every one of these cases
we see mortality connected with their
experience
and so we then
generalize we come to the conclusion
from the particular
this man dies that man dies this man
dies this man to every person we've ever
known has died
and so we come the conclusion well this
must be something that is shared in
common by every human being
but do we know it for sure
in other words have we
had an empirical experience
of every human being
who has ever lived
how do we know that the generation that
we make up is not the first generation
in all of human history
to be immortal
or we laugh at that because we say well
that's just
inconceivable no it isn't inconceivable
it's just extremely improbable
astronomically improbable
in light of the pattern and the history
of the examples that we have
now
can I ever know
with certainty that all men are mortal
well you can say
we can have a nuclear war and every
person that's now alive in the universe
is annihilated and I I alone am left
and now I can come to the conclusion
that everybody that's who's ever lived
has died
so I now know for sure that all men are
mortal what's wrong with that picture
maybe I'm the singular exception in all
of human history
and maybe I am not mortal so that the
only way I can know for sure that all
men are mortal is posthumously see
that's the limit of induction we can
never have a fully exhaustive collection
of individual examples
but we don't need to wait to examine
every squirrel or every human being
before we have a working knowledge of
universals
or what we call scientific laws that if
we once arrive at a certain number of
examples that prove to be true
individually then we universalize or
generalize
now there's a reason
why I'm backing up and going through all
of this because again what was
motivating the thinkers in the 17th
century was I want to get to that realm
of knowledge
that's absolutely certain
100 percent certain
no plus or minus three percent
and the empiricists come along and say
well the only place you can find a
hundred percent certainty is in the
formal realm of reasoning of the
relationship of different ideas to each
other
but how does that get you to the real
world and it doesn't and so the
empiricists like John Locke are coming
along and they're saying with their
tabula rasa concept no no no no no
the only way we know anything initially
is by having an experience of it we see
it taste it touches we're from Missouri
we're from the show me state don't just
theorize about these things give me
empirical evidence that such and such a
thing is true now that's part of the the
framework and fabric of our culture
today isn't it I mean we hear this all
the time don't talk to me about what you
believe in God and all of that sort of
thing and these rational arguments that
you get for the existence of God I want
to see him
I want to hear them
show me the money
show me the deity because if I have an
empirical perception of it
then I know for sure well
unfortunately
the more your knowledge rests upon sense
perception
the less certain it can possibly be
because of this problem and because of
the limitations involved in looking at
each and every possible example
so
empiricism
is always Limited
by the finite samples that we have to
study
and it's always vulnerable and exposed
to the possibility that the next
discovery will present a gigantic
anomaly
an anomaly is something that doesn't fit
the pattern
an anomaly is something that can't be
explained by the system
and when you have too many anomalies
coming
you have to throw away the system and
create what we call a whole new model or
a whole new paradigm you've heard the
expression paradigm shift
which means a shift in the model A
change in the model and Paradise shifts
are in science are driven by anomalies
things that don't fit the old model that
say we're going to have to broaden that
model or scrap part of the model come up
with a new model that will help us get a
handle
on reality
so in addition to this as we progress
through history
with the Advent of science as we move
rushing into the 18th century
two things were happening on the one
hand
the world was getting bigger
well I don't mean by that that it was
growing
but our understanding the human
perception of the world was increasing
dramatically
principally
through the discovery and the use of the
telescope
we realized that there was far more out
there than anybody ever imagined and
that we were living in a neighborhood we
call the universe that was Far bigger
than anybody had ever anticipated
and yet not only did we find that the
world was getting bigger
but also that the world was getting
smaller
the world was getting smaller
with the discovery of the microscope
we began to see a whole realm of reality
that we never knew existed in fact we've
come to understand
that so much of our lives
are dependent upon things that are out
there
in that objective world
that we can't see taste touch or smell
with our naked senses
we need more advanced tools like
microscopes to even realize that there's
all this activity going on at the
microscopic level that can affect our
very existence we see that in the field
of medicine when microbodies are
invading our organic health and
destroying it and so on so these
problems
push the philosophers constantly
to sharpen their understanding of two
things
what is real
and how do we get
to what is real